Guide to the Leroy E. Burney Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Leroy E. Burney papers
1931-1978
MS 842
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
12
(29 boxes)
Chiefly office files from Burney's tenure as vice-president and executive director of the Milbank Memorial Fund, 1970-1977. (The fund is an organization dedicated to studying and promoting the effective delivery of health services.) Included in the papers are correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, budget summaries, reports and the records for three programs supported by the Fund: the African Medical Education Program, the Commission for the Study of Higher Education for Public Health, and the Human Resources Development Project. Burney's activities in various organizations and commissions devoted to health care are documented in correspondence and files on these groups. Of particular interest are the files for the controversial President's Committee on Health Education, created by President Nixon in 1971. Burney's writings include texts of speeches, reports, drafts of articles, and offprints (1937-1976). Significant corrspondents in the papers are Florence Kavaler, Cecil G. Sheps, David Willis, Lester Breslow and Elliot L. Richardson. There is also a small amount of biographical material including photographs, family correspondence, biographical sketches, clippings and awards. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Burney, Leroy E. (Leroy Edgar), 1906-1998
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Leroy Burney, 1978.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Professional Activities. II. Writings. III. Biographical Files.
Scope and Contents
The Burney Papers consist of twelve linear feet of office files from his service with the Milbank Memorial Fund, other professional files, reprints, speech texts and a few biographical files. The papers date primarily from 1970 to 1976 but include a few materials from 1936 forward. They are organized in three series: PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES, WRITINGS, and BIOGRAPHICAL FILES.
The bulk of the PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES series dates from the 1970s. The series is organized in three sections: Milbank Memorial Fund, Other Activities and Reference. The first section consists of a limited number of personal office files which Burney retained following his retirement from the fund, divided between General Files and Program Records. The General Files are arranged alphabetically and consist of Burney's outgoing correspondence and letters, announcements, mimeographed memoranda, reports, and speech texts which he received from associates in medicine and public health, Milbank colleagues, and professional organizations. Much of the correspondence is routine, although the files for Florence Kavaler, Cecil G. Sheps, and David Willis contain discussions and information on the fund's Commission for the Study of Higher Education for Public Health. The exchanges with Lester Breslow concern specific public health education programs. An uncharacteristically lengthy letter to Secretary of Health, Education, and Welfare Elliot L. Richardson presents detailed defense of the Public Health Service Commissioned Corps.
The Program Records in the Milbank Memorial Fund section are arranged chronologically by topic and include general administrative papers (e.g., correspondence, minutes, budget summaries, reports), and files for three fund programs: the African Medical Education Program, the Commission for the Study of Higher Education for Public Health, and the Human Resources Development project. Much of the material in Program Records is fragmented and concerns routine administrative and operational matters, but the Commission for the Study of Higher Education files provide extensive documentation of its organization and activities.
The Other Activities section of Series I is arranged alphabetically by organization and contains files from Burney's participation in several committees and commissions. The section also contains a few financial and administrative records and some correspondence from his service as health commissioner and secretary of the Indiana State Board of Health and two folders, consisting primarily of print material, from his tenure as vice president for health sciences in Temple University.
The bulk of the section consists of files for organizations in which Burney played an active role while he was with the Milbank Fund: the National Commission for the Study of Nursing and Nursing Education, the the National Council for International Health, the National Health Council, and the President's Committee on Health Education. Burney became president of the board of commissioners of the National Commission for the Study of Nursing Education in January 1971, and he served in both an advisory role and as a spokesman before state nursing groups. The papers (1971-1976) include correspondence, minutes, and reports, and the annual narrative report for October 1970 to September 1971, which summarizes the commission's organizations and objectives. The National Council for International Health subsection (1972-1976) reflects Burney's interest in international health issues and contains a complete run of agenda books for the period covered by the papers. Burney served as president (1968-1969) and as a member of the board of directors of the National Health Council, and the subsection (1968-1971) contains a relatively large amount of correspondence on administrative and operational matters.
The files of the President's Committee on Health Education, which was created by President Nixon in 1971, are of special interest; they reflect both national politics in the early 1970s and Burney's interest in health consumerism. The papers cover the extensive research conducted by the committee to develop a plan to raise the level of "health consumer citizenship" and the dissension which hindered the drafting of the final report. A memorandum from Victor Weingarten (1973 Jun 20) describes why the White House impounded the committees's printed report.
The Reference section is arranged chronologically and contains miscellaneous reprints, mostly from the late 1960s and the 1970s, on a variety of, general health-oriented topics.
Series II, WRITINGS, is arranged chronologically and spans the years 1937 to 1976. The series is extensive and is made up of reprints, speech texts, reports, and drafts of articles and other writings. The files occasionally include correspondence and reference material. The series contains bound volumes of Burney's speeches for the years 1954 to 1958.
Series III, BIOGRAPHICAL FILES, is arranged chronologically and consists of eight folders of biographical sketches, awards, photographs, newsclippings and related material.
The Burney Papers were donated to the Department of Manuscripts and Archives by Dr. Burney in 1978. The papers are part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection, which also includes the Milbank Memorial Fund Records (Ms. Group 845).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Leroy E. Burney had a dinstinguished career in public health administration. Among other positions, he has served as Surgeon General of the United States Public Health Service (1956-1961) and President of the Milbank Memorial Fund (1974-1977). Born in Burney, Indiana, he was educated at Butler University (1924-1926), the University of Indiana (B.S. 1928; M.D., 1930) and Johns Hopkins University (M.P.H., 1932). Burney was commissioned in the Regular Corps of the U.S. Public Health Service in 1932, and for the next thirty years he served in a variety of assignments. From 1945 to 1954 he held the position of health commissioner and secretary of the Indiana State Board of Health, on detail from the Public Health Service. He was appointed Assistant Surgeon General in 1954 and Surgeon General in 1956.
During Burney's term as Surgeon General, the Public Health Service initiated and expanded programs in environmental health and applied research, including studies of the relationship between cancer and cigarette smoking and new measures for the prevention of poliomyelitis. Believing strongly in the efficacy of public education, Burney was one of the first officials to warn the nation that "excessive cigarette smoking is a causative factor in lung cancer." He also convened the first national conference on air and water pollution. Burney's other areas of activity as Surgeon General included expansion of international health programs and efforts at administrative reorganization. After leaving the Public Health Service in 1961, he served as the first vice president of health sciences at Temple University, until his appointment as vice president and executive director of the Milbank Memorial Fund in September 1970.
Since its founding in 1905 the Milbank Memorial Fund had concentrated on successive, specific issues in endeavoring to improve and reform the delivery of health service. Following Burney's appointment as vice president and executive director in September 1970 and as president in January 1971, the fund reoriented its program to focus on the health services consumer and especially on the acquisition and application of knowledge about more effective utilization of health services. Burney also established a Commission for the Study of Higher Education for Public Health to explore needs in the field. Burney retired from the Milbank Fund in December 1977.
In addition to his professional appointments, Burney had been active in a variety of public health, international health and civic organizations and has served on a number of national commissions and committees. His work with the World Health Assembly (president, 1957) was especially significance.
Health education; Medicine; Patient education; Public health -- Research; Health services administrators; Physicians; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Breslow, Lester; Burney, Leroy E. (Leroy Edgar), 1906-1998; Ebert, Robert Higgins, 1914-; Gruenberg, Ernest M., 1915-; Kavaler, Florence; Richardson, Elliot L., 1920-1999; Sheps, Cecil G. (Cecil George), 1913-2004; Silver, George A., 1913-; Willis, David Peter, 1930-; Milbank Memorial Fund; United States President's Committee on Health Education
- PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES, 1931-(1960-1978); Series I; 9' (21 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES is organized in three sections: Milbank Memorial Fund, Other Professional Activities, and Reference. The Milbank Memorial Fund section is organized in two subsections; the first subsection is arranged alphabetically and the second is arranged chronologically. The other two sections are arranged chronologically. Files designated with an asterisk contain ten or more items.
  Folders with asterisks(*) contain ten or more items
  - Milbank Memorial Fund
    - General Files
      - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - American Sociological Association, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Medical Care Section (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Association for Academic Health Centers, 1972, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
      - Association of American Medical Colleges, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Association of American Medical Colleges, Division of International Medical Education, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Association of Schools of Public Health, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        General
        See also: box 7, folders 107-127
      - Atkinson, Joe W., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Austin, Charles J., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - B (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Baehr, George, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Baker, Timothy D., 1973, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Blankenship, Charles F., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Boudreau, Frank G., 1958, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Breslow, Lester (*), 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Buford, Albert, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - C (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Chamber of Commerce of the United States, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Commission on Education for Health Administration
        See: box 1, folder 8
      - Community Conference on Health Aides in Antigua West Indies), 1975 March-April (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Conference on Future Directions in Health Care, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - D (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Dixon, James P., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        See also: box 2, folder 37
      - E (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Ebert, Robert H (*)., 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - F (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Fruchtbaum, Harold, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - G (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Godber, George E., 1972, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Gruenberg, Ernest (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - H (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Healey, James S., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Hyde, Henry van Zile, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - I - K (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - International Conference on the Physician and Population Change
        See: box 2, folder 28
      - International Health Resource Consortium
        See: box 3, folder 44
      - Kaiser-Permanente Medical Care Program, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Kasius, Richard V., 1976 March 8 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Kavaler, Florence (*), 1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Kavaler, Florence (*), 1973 March-October (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Kavaler, Florence, 1973 November-December (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Kavaler, Florence (*), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Kavaler, Florence (*), 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Kellogg Commission
      - Kellogg, W. K. Foundation, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - L (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - M (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Mahler, Halfdan
        See: box 4, folder 70
      - Mawby, Russell G.
        See: box 2, folder 37
      - N (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Newell, Kenneth W.
      - O (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - P (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Pattullo, Andrew
      - Payne, Fred J., 1974 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Pearson, Clarence E., 1977 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - President's Committee on Health Education
        See: box 10, folder 142
      - Richardson, Arthur H., 1972 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Richardson, Elliot, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Rosemond, George P., 1972 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Runnerstrom, Lillian, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - S (Box 3, Folder 47)
      - Sheps, Cecil G. (*), 1972 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      - Sheps, Cecil G. (*), 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 49-52)
      - Sheps, Cecil G., [1975-1976] (Box 3, Folder 53)
      - Sheps, Cecil G. (*), 1976 January-April (Box 3, Folder 54-55)
      - Sheps, Cecil G. (*), 1976 May-1977 (Box 4, Folder 56-58)
      - Shimkin, Michael B. (*), 1972-1977 (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - Siegel, Milton, 1972, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 60)
      - Silver, George A., 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 61)
      - Somers, Herman M., 1975 (Box 4, Folder 61)
      - Soper, Fred L., 1973 (Box 4, Folder 61)
      - Souder, James J., 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 62)
      - Strauss, Janet A., 1976 (Box 4, Folder 63)
      - Strauss, Marvin, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 63)
      - Stuart, Kenneth L., 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 64)
      - Suter, Emanuel
        See: box 1, folder 5
      - Taubenhaus, Marjorie, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 65)
      - Timmons, Gerald D., 1974 (Box 4, Folder 66)
      - United States Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Office of Aging, 1974 July 8 (Box 4, Folder 67)
      - W (Box 4, Folder 68)
      - White, Kerr L.
        See: box 7, folder 107
      - Willis, David P. (*), 1971-1977 (Box 4, Folder 69)
      - Wolman, Abel, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 69)
      - World Health Organization, 1970-1976 (Box 4, Folder 70)
        See also: box 24, folder 92
        See also: box 25, folder 126
      - Y (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Program Records
      - General
        - Correspondence, 1963-1968 (Box 4, Folder 72)
        - News releases and clippings, 1966-1970, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 73)
        - Annual report, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 74)
        - Annual report of president and treasurer, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 75)
        - Financial statements and budget, 1968-1969, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 76)
        - Correspondence, 1969 January-October (Box 5, Folder 77)
        - Correspondence re: appointment, 1969 November-1969 December 1-30 (Box 5, Folder 78-80)
        - Correspondence re: appointments and operations, 1970 January-October (Box 5, Folder 81-82)
        - Memoranda and pamphlets re: retirement and medical insurance, 1970, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 83)
        - Memoranda re: administration matters, 1970-1976 (Box 5, Folder 84)
        - Correspondence re: appointment, 1971 January-April (Box 5, Folder 85)
        - Proposed program for fund, 1971 October (Box 5, Folder 86)
        - Recommendations re: Technical Board, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 87)
        - Correspondence and related material re: faculty fellows and associates, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 88)
        - "Major Program Objective", 1971-1975 (Box 6, Folder 89)
        - Minutes and memoranda, Technical Board, 1971-1977 (Box 6, Folder 90)
        - Summary statement of program, 1972 January (Box 6, Folder 91)
        - Pamphlet and drafts, Current Program Policy and Organization, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 92)
        - Memoranda and minutes, Board of Directors, 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 93)
        - Correspondence, 1972-1975, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 94)
        - Summary budgets, 1972-1976 (Box 6, Folder 95)
        - Grant proposals and related material, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 96)
        - Office directory, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 97)
        - Memoranda, Board of Directors, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 98)
        - Background statement to proposed program, undated (Box 6, Folder 99)
      - African Medical Education Program
        - Background material, 1963-1968 (Box 6, Folder 100)
        - Report re: African trip (Yale University), 1968 (Box 6, Folder 101)
        - Background material, 1969-1970, undated (Box 6, Folder 102)
        - Report and recommendations, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 103)
        - Reports and notes, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 104)
        - Memorandum and correspondence, 1973, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 105)
        - Report on review visits (Burney, J. S. Baugh), 1974 March (Box 6, Folder 106)
      - Commission for the Study of Higher Education for Public Health
        - Background material, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 107)
        - Background material and notes, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 108)
        - Position paper, 1972 May (Box 7, Folder 109)
        - Press releases, 1972 June-November (Box 7, Folder 110)
        - Agenda and working papers, first meeting, 1972 October (Box 7, Folder 111)
        - Background material, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 112)
        - "General Principles for Administrative Structure", 1972 (Box 7, Folder 113)
        - Study proposals, notes and related material, 1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 114)
        - List of members and biographical material, 1972-1974 (Box 7, Folder 115)
        - Progress reports, 1972, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 116)
        - Agenda, minutes and working papers, third meeting, 1973 April (Box 7, Folder 117)
        - History and related material, 1973 Oct, undated (Box 7, Folder 118)
        - Agenda, minutes and working papers, fifth meeting, 1973 December (Box 8, Folder 119)
        - Agenda, minutes and working papers, sixth meeting, 1974 February (Box 8, Folder 120)
        - Agenda, minutes and working papers, seventh meeting, 1974 May (Box 8, Folder 121)
        - Final report drafts, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 122)
        - Preliminary report, 1975 January (Box 8, Folder 123)
        - Final report drafts, 1975 March-May (Box 8, Folder 124)
        - Final report outline, 1975 November (Box 8, Folder 125)
        - Final report, 1975 November (Box 9, Folder 126)
        - Reports re: Impact of final report (C. Sheps), 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 127)
      - Human Resources Development project
        - Memoranda re: objectives and guidelines, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 128)
        - Bulletin and newsclippings, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 129)
        - Reports and related material, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 130)
        - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 131)
        - Conference report, 1973 February (Box 9, Folder 132)
  - Other Activities
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1957-1958, 1963-1977 (Box 9, Folder 133)
    - American Fund for Dental Health
      - Correspondence, minutes and background material, 1971, 1975-1977 (Box 9, Folder 134-135)
      - Reports, releases and statements, 1970-1977 (Box 9, Folder 136)
    - American Medical Association
      - Task Force on International Medicine
        - Correspondence and minutes, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 137)
        - Correspondence and study proposal, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 138)
          See also: box 12, folders 193-215
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 139)
    - American Public Health Association: correspondence re: annual meeting, 1973-1977 (Box 10, Folder 140)
    - Boy Scouts of America: correspondence, reports and background material, 1970-1973 (Box 10, Folder 141)
    - Consumer Health Education Conference agenda, correspondence and proceedings, 1973-1975 (Box 10, Folder 142)
    - Excerpta Medica: correspondence and pamphlets, 1975-1978 (Box 10, Folder 143)
    - Indiana State Board of Health
      - Maps and releases re: administrative decentralization, Circa 1947-1948 (Box 10, Folder 144)
      - Health law codification
        - Correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 10, Folder 145-146)
        - Outlines, releases and background papers, 1948, undated (Box 10, Folder 147)
        - State senate bill 39, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 148)
      - Building dedication
        - Correspondence, program and speech text, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 149)
        - Invitation lists, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 150)
      - "Budget Justification", 1951-1965 (Box 10, Folder 151-152)
    - Johns Hopkins University
      - Visiting Committee for the School of Hygiene and Public Health: correspondence and reports, 1967-1969 (Box 10, Folder 153)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence and leaflets, 1970-1975 (Box 11, Folder 154)
      - Ad Hoc Review Committee
        - Correspondence and background material, 1972 August-1973, undated (Box 11, Folder 155-156)
        - Report (with drafts), 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 157)
      - Conference for Alumni Educators: correspondence and transcript, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 158)
      - Johns Hopkins Society of Scholars: correspondence, itineraries and program, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 159)
    - National Commission for the Study of Nursing and Nursing Education
      - Summary report and recommendations, 1970 February (Box 11, Folder 160)
      - Correspondence, 1970 July-December (Box 11, Folder 161)
      - Monthly memoranda, 1970 August-December (Box 11, Folder 162)
      - Fund balance, 1970 September (Box 11, Folder 163)
      - Annual financial reports, 1970 oct-1972 September (Box 11, Folder 164)
      - Agenda, 1970 November-1972 October (Box 11, Folder 165)
      - Memoranda, 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 166)
      - State Publications, 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 167)
      - Reference material, 1970-1972, undated (Box 11, Folder 168)
      - Monthly memoranda, 1971 January-December (Box 11, Folder 169)
      - Report (and preliminary draft) re: physicians assistants, 1971 February 12 (Box 11, Folder 170)
      - Press releases, 1971 February-September (Box 11, Folder 171)
      - Notes (Burney?), 1971 October (Box 11, Folder 172)
      - Annual reports and supplementary report on target state implementation, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 173)
      - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 174)
      - Public relations proposals, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 175)
      - Publications, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 176)
      - Summary report and recommendations, reviews and publication re: An Abstract for Action, 1971, undated (Box 12, Folder 177)